Guide to the G. & C. Merriam Company Records
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
G. & C. Merriam Company records
1830-1935
GEN MSS 789
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.34
(3 boxes)
The records consist correspondence, advertisements, invoices, bills of lading, circulars and other papers relating to the G. & C. Merriam Company's wholesale and retail book trade. Includes records relating to Claremont Manufacturing Company and H.H. Bancroft and Company.
G. & C. Merriam Company
General note
This finding aid describes a collection that has been acquired by the library in discrete segments over time. The narrative sections of the finding aid provide information about the content and context of the collection. The Collection Contents section provides a general description and in some instances a box or folder listing of the various acquisitions of the collection. The Processing Notes section provides information about the way and extent to which the library has processed this collection. The Arrangement section provides information about how material within this collection is organized and tips on how to locate material across various acquisitions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Eclectibles, 2010, on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, from M & S Rare Books, Inc., 2010, on the Hall Park McCullough Fund, and from Lawbook Exchange, Ltd., 2011, on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
G. & C. Merriam Company Archive. General Collection, Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
G. & C. Merriam Company
The G. & C. Merriam Company, established by George and Charles Merriam in Springfield, Massachusetts, was the publisher and reviser of Noah Webster's American Dictionary beginning in 1847.
Scope and Contents
The records consist correspondence, advertisements, invoices, bills of lading, circulars and other papers relating to the G. & C. Merriam Company's wholesale and retail book trade. Includes records relating to Claremont Manufacturing Company and H.H. Bancroft and Company.
Arrangement
Organized into two groupings: July and October 2010 Acquisitions, and August 2011 Acquisition.
Booksellers and bookselling -- United States; Publishers and publishing -- United States; Advertisements; Business records; Claremont Manufacturing Company; G. & C. Merriam Company; H.H. Bancroft and Company
- July and October 2010 Acquisitions, 1830s-1935; 3.34; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Material is arranged in rough alphabetical order.
  - A Key to Uncle Tom's Cabin - publicity flyer, 1853 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes a handwritten letter on the reverse.
  - Advertisements, 1850s-1930s (Box 1)
  - Advertisement, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Advertising - receipts, 1830s-1850s (Box 1)
  - American Seamen's Friend Society - printed brochure with letter from L. P. Hubbard, 1865 (Box 1)
  - Banks, Gould & Co. - handwritten invoice, 1847 (Box 1)
  - A Book for the Million! - broadside circular, 1853 (Box 1)
  - Book lists, 1850s (Box 1)
  - Books Published by T. R. Marvin - printed circular, 1844 (Box 1)
    Includes a handwritten letter on reverse from T.R. Marvin concerning a book order.
  - Boston Trade Sale circulars, 1844-1851 (Box 1)
  - Business cards, advertisements, promotional pamphlets, etc. (Box 1)
  - Business correspondence, 1830s-1870s; 3 (Box 1)
  - Business papers, 1830s-1860s; 3 (Box 1)
  - Business papers - H. H. Bancroft & Co., 1850s-1860s (Box 1)
  - Business papers - San Francisco, 1860s-1870s (Box 1)
  - Business papers - Sunday School Unions, 1830s-1860s (Box 1)
  - Checks, 1840s-1850s (Box 1)
  - Circulars (Box 1)
  - Circulars - trade sales, 1830s-1850s (Box 1)
  - Claremont Manufacturing Company, 1840-1860 (Box 1)
  - Cole, Robert H. - letter requesting books, 1844 (Box 1)
  - Copyright certificates, 1836-1840 (Box 1)
  - The Elements of Intellectual Philosophy - printed circular, 1855 (Box 1)
    Includes a handwritten letter on the reverse from Philips and Sampson.
  - Graves, J. R., 1871 (Box 1)
  - J. & A. MacMillan sales, 1866 (Box 1)
  - Jones, Henry and J. Hammond Trumbull - correspondence, 1864-1866 (Box 1)
  - Key wallets (Box 1)
    Contains three G. & C. Merriam Co. key wallets.
  - Lists of Books Published, 1830s-1850s; 3 (Box 1)
  - List of Books Published and Offered to the Trade of John P. Jewett, 1843 (Box 1)
    Includes a bill for books ordered by Merriam, found on reverse.
  - Papers relating to publishing, 1830s-1840s (Box 1)
  - The Paramount Question! Is the Existence of a Privileged Class Compatible with the Theoretical Equality of Republican Institutions? - printed circular, 1855 (Box 1)
  - People's History of America, 1874 (Box 1)
  - Printer's correspondence, 1852-1870 (Box 1)
    Contains five letters and two receipts.
  - Program and menu for dinner to announce second edition, 1934 June 25 (Box 1)
  - Promotional materials - loose-leaf papers, 1850s (Box 1)
  - Promotional materials - pamphlets, 1861-1935 (Box 1)
  - Prospectus of Lowe's Farm and Fireside Journal - printed circular, 1867 (Box 1)
    Includes a letter from J. Payne Lowe on the reverse.
  - Prospectus of the New York Recorder - printed ciruclar, 1852 (Box 1)
    Includes a handwritten letter from James S. Dickinson & Co. on the reverse.
  - Publishing and advertisement, 1830s-1860s (Box 1)
  - Purchases - Hartford and New Haven - receipts, 1840s-1850s (Box 1)
  - Purchases - Benjamin Olds - receipts, 1840s (Box 1)
  - Purchases - Other New England receipts, 1830s-1840s (Box 1)
  - Purchases - various receipts, 1840s-1870s; 2 (Box 1)
  - Receipts and business correspondence, 1830s-1860s (Box 2)
  - Receipts and correspondence, 1830s-1860s; 3 (Box 2)
  - Sales papers, 1830s-1870s; 2 (Box 2)
  - Sales, advertisements and related correspondence, 1840s-1860s (Box 2)
  - Sales, publishing, shipping, 1840s-1870s (Box 2)
  - Sessions, William H. - letter concerning a debt, 1845 (Box 2)
  - Shipping, 1860 (Box 2)
  - Shipping - Bills of Landing from Clipper Ships to San Francisco, 1850s-1860s (Box 2)
  - Shipping - Bills of Landing - Railroads, Ships, 1850s-1860s (Box 2)
  - Shipping - Railroads - Boston and Worcester Railroad - receipts, 1830s-1840s (Box 2)
  - Shipping - Railroads - Conn. River Railroad Co. - receipts, 1840s-1850s (Box 2)
  - Shipping - Railroads - Hartford-New Haven Railroad, 1840s-1850s (Box 2)
  - Shipping - Railroads - receipts, 1830s-1850s; 2 (Box 2)
  - Shipping - Railroads - receipts and correspondence, 1840s-1860s; 2 (Box 2)
  - Shipping - Railroads and steamboats - receipts, 1830s-1850s (Box 2)
  - Shipping - Railroads - Western Railroad Corporation, 1840s-1870s; 2 (Box 2)
  - Shipping - Steamboat - New Haven Steamboat Co. - receipts, 1860s (Box 2)
  - Shipping - Steamboats - receipts, 1830s-1850s (Box 2)
  - Shipping - Steamboats and ships - receipts, 1830s-1850s (Box 2)
  - Shipping - Transportation Lines - receipts, 1830s-1850s (Box 2)
  - Shipping - Transportation Lines - Union Transportation Line, 1840s (Box 2)
  - Shipping - Various receipts, 1830s-1870s; 4 (Box 2)
  - Small plastic dictionaries (Box 2)
  - Subscription to The Emancipator, New York - printed receipt, 1838 (Box 2)
  - Swett, John - letters, 1860s (Box 2)
  - Warren, J.Q.A. - letters to Merriam and Advertising card, 1859 (Box 2)
  - Webster & Merriam portraits (Box 2)
  - Works of Daniel Webster promotional proposal - circular, 1851 (Box 2)
    Includes a handwritten letter on the reverse, concerning a book order from Little Brown and Company.
  - 100th Anniversary booklet, 1931 (Box 2)
  - Printed ephemera (Box 3 Oversize)
- August 2011 Acquisition, 1833-1869
  - Correspondence, financial papers and printed material, 1833-1869; 3 (Box 2)